# 十五个饺子能吃出三种味道来
We can have three flavors in these 15 dumplings
# 开锅煮馅 闭锅煮皮
Uncover it to cook the filling, and cover it to cook the skin
# 好了 三鲜馅的
Alright, Sanxian filling (pork, shrimps, sea cucumbers, chives) dumplings
# 不管是高筋低筋的
It doesn’t matter whether you got high- or low-gluten flour
# 我们和面当中要搁点盐
We need some salt in the dough
# 使这面更加有劲 别太多
So that it’s stiffer but don’t add too much
# 饺子面要注意 有一句话叫
There’s a saying for the dumpling dough:
# 软面饺子 硬面汤
Soft dough for dumplings and stiff dough for soup
# 饺子面子比烙饼面稍微硬点
The dumpling dough should be a little stiffer than the pancake dough
# 比面条面稍微软点
And a little softer than the noodle dough
# 和面也得匀着往里加水 和的才滋润
Add water gradually when you are kneading the dough so it’s even
# 好了 咱们开始揣揣
Alright let’s knead it into a dough
# 盆光面光手光 三光
The surfaces of the pot, the dough and your hands should be clean at last
# 您这三鲜馅够豪华
It’s a deluxe choice of Sanxian fillings
# 有时候我在家里要没有海参的时候
When we could not find some sea cucumbers
# 也可以找一个东西替海参
We could have an alternative for that
# 你知道什么么
Guess what?
# 木耳 木耳也挺脆的
It’s the wood ears because they are also crunchy
# 行了 然后让它饧一会儿
Alright, let it rest for a while
# 猪肉 虾仁 海参 韭菜
Pork, shrimps, sea cucumbers and chives
# 我这儿开始准备准备馅儿
I’ll start making the fillings
# 海参这肠有的人不爱去
Some will forget to remove the intestine of sea cucumbers
# 有时候不去它腥
But it has a bad smell
# 找个小锅给它出一下水
Grab a small pot and boil the sea cucumbers
# 来两片姜 来点酒 黄酒
Two slices of garlic with some huangjiu rice wine in the water
# 再来几个葱 还得搁点盐
Also some green onions and some salt
# 这去掉海参的腥味和给它增加点味道
These remove the bad smell of sea cucumbers and add some flavors to it
# 然后咱把虾仁给它处理一下
Now let’s deal with the shrimps
# 这虾仁买的是现成的
These are store bought
# 这虾线都挑干净了
and deveined
# 现在这海鲜便宜 比吃肉还便宜 白菜价
Now it’s cheaper to have seafood than meat. Almost like cabbages
# 水开了海参下锅 开锅五分钟
Sea cucumbers in the boiling water and boil them for 5 minutes
# 剩下虾就不拍了 让它有点颗粒度
We won’t need to splash the rest shrimps, remain some texture
# 这个您是想和到馅儿里么
So these shrimps are for the fillings?
# 对 但是分头打 分头调味
Yeah but we season the pork and shrimps separately
# 因为肉馅儿的味儿重 虾馅的要轻
Because the meat need strong seasoning while shrimps need light seasoning
# 要混在一块调 容易虾就咸了
If seasoned them together, the shrimps will be too salty
# 齐了 真黏糊
Alright, it’s so sticky
# 好了 拿出来
Alright, grab the sea cucumbers
# 这海参可多可少
The amount of sea cucumber depends (on your preference)
# 爱吃的就是虾仁 海参 少搁肉
If you like it, then put more shrimps and sea cucumbers and less meat
# 这点就基本上一个饺子里有一个海参丁
With these, it’s basically just having one piece of sea cucumber in every dumpling
# 来点姜米 有韭菜不搁葱 一定要记住了
Also some chopped ginger. No need for green onions when we have chives, keep that in mind.
# 肉馅是这样
The meat fillings is like this
# 一般咱们家里头都拿筷子打馅儿
We usually mix the ground meat with chopsticks
# 筷子打馅就慢
That way is too slow
# 上手打 酱油
Just use your hands. Some soy sauce
# 这个肉馅的比例就是买肥瘦
Keep a good portion of fat in the ground pork
# 肥三瘦七 前腿
Thirty percent fat. That’s usually pork legs
# 首先抓抓
Grab a few times first
# 打馅不加料酒 可以加味精
Don’t put cooking wine yet but some MSG
# 盐 这饺子馅儿必须得味重
Some salt. The fillings must have strong flavor
# 不味重它不好吃
Otherwise it’s not good
# 少来 这要颜色的 老抽
A little bit of Laochou dark soy sauce for the color
# 这个馅还得要摔摔它
The ground pork fillings need to be beaten
# 以前的肉都是养一年的猪
Long time ago, all the pork come from pigs older than one year
# 它肉香味浓 您多打点水没事
Those pork have strong flavors and you can mix more water in the fillings
# 稍微打点水可以
A little bit more water
# 现在肉打多了就没味了
But the pork these days will be bland with too much water in the fillings
# 摔得有劲 包饺子容易抱团
Beaten enough, the fillings can easily get to a ball inside the skins
# 抱团还出汁儿呐
Also juicier
# 虾肉 海参丁 姜米放进 去
Shrimps, sea cucumber pieces, ginger pieces, in
# 这一抓挠 把荤馅打完了以后
When the meat filings are ready
# 如果说我们一小时两小时以后才包呢
If there is still time before making the dumplings
# 就放在冰箱里头 让它镇一镇
Let the fillings rest in the fridge
# 素馅不要着急往里边一块和
Don’t rush chopping the veggies and putting them in
# 什么时候包什么时候和 来油
Mix the veggies with the meat just before making dumplings. Now some oil in
# 就仗着这油呢 多搁点油没事 花生油
The oil is really important and add much to it. Peanut oil
# 香油 二合油 这叫什么
Also some sesame oil mixed. What’s this called?
# 按照咱们老北京话说 这叫味上馅
In our Beijing dialect, it’s putting flavors in the fillings
# 你看这馅儿倍儿腻乎
See how sticky the fillings is now
# 味好了 切韭菜
Enough with the flavors, now chop the chives
# 咱择韭菜的时候 我们在家里择韭菜
When we are picking the chives at home
# 拿剪子 最后把根给去了
Use a pair of scissors to cut the roots
# 为什么这上边 有时候搁韭菜有沙子
Why? Sometimes chives have sand.
# 第一刀有时候就不要了
Leave the first chop off
# 一入秋 一过国庆节就可以吃韭菜了
The chive season start at autumn, after the National Day
# 现在的韭菜正香
The chives are the best right now
# 买韭菜买那紫根的 比这个细
The ones with purple roots are better, which is a bit thinner
# 那个韭菜是更香 那叫鸡脖韭
That one has a better smell and it has a nickname, called "chicken neck chives"
# 咱就搁在里头了
Now let’s put the chives in there
# 什么时候包 什么时候和
Mix the veggies in the fillings just before making the dumplings
# 老早和了你要不包 一会儿塌了
The (vegetable) will loss water if you mix them too early
# 老北京还一讲头 饺子要吃热的
People in Beijing also prefer hot dumplings
# 吃五个煮五个
Boil five, eat five
# 另外吃饺子能吃出三种味道来
Also, there are three ways to taste the dumplings
# 第一个五个饺子 什么都不蘸
Dip nothing for the first five dumplings
# 你要吃我的馅的鲜美的味道
To taste the freshness and the original flavor of the fillings
# 第二个五个 搁点醋
The next five dumplings can go with vinegar
# 吃醋和饺子馅的美味
To taste the flavor of vinegar along with dumplings
# 第三种味道
The third taste
# 少搁点酱油 搁点红油 搁点烂蒜
A little bit of soy sauce, chili oil and garlic pieces
# 十五个饺子能吃出三种味道来
Three tastes for 15 dumplings
# 咱们现在看看面好了没有
Now let’s see whether the dough is ready
# 这面差不多了
It seems about right
# 这面揉完了还得饧一下
After kneading it again, let it rest again
# 再饧三分钟五分钟
For another 3-5 minutes
# 亮子咱开剂儿
Lianzi, let’s split the dough
# 这面雪白
It’s so white
# 您揪啊您不切 我不切 我是半专业
You’re pulling instead of cutting. Yeah I’m semi-professional
# 揪劲儿是这样
Pulling like this
# 我跟原来师傅看他们揪的时候
I watched the older cooks pulling it
# 这边捏住了
Nip this end like this
# 这手捏住了
And grab some dough like this
# 这是一个剂儿 准确度
One, there you go. Be precise
# 这儿一使劲 往下一硌
Pull like this and drop that
# 但是跟专业的老师
Compared to professional bakers
# 可能有的方法还不太准确
It may not be perfect
# 擀剂儿
Roll this small piece of dough
# 您这娴熟的手法
Whoa, you are so good at this
# 一看您也在家里边经常包 经常做
I guess you often make dumplings at home too
# 这时候可以攉拢到一块去了
Now we mix the veggies into the fillings
# 韭菜碧绿碧绿的
Look at how green the chives are
# 包饺子是这样的
Making dumplings is like this
# 在饭店里边就学会了挤饺子
I learnt how to make dumplings in a restaurant
# 我老捏不好这头
I always have problem nipping this end
# 我就先把这头给它封上
So I first seal this end
# 一挤 倍儿棒
Then nip the dumpling. There you go
# 我们家包饺子就是馅比较大
Dumplings in my house have big portion of fillings
# 吃饺子要有仪式感 皮儿薄馅儿足
It has a special festival feeling with thin skins and a lot of fillings
# 大爷包的还挺快
Daye is making so many dumplings
# 煮饺子也有点小窍门
There is also a trick for boiling the dumplings
# 我们给它煮的时候搁点盐
Put some salt in the boiling water
# 它互相不爱粘
So that the dumplings won’t stick to each other
# 宽水 上盖
Wide boiling water, lid on
# 煮饺子的时候一定要让它悬起来
When we are boiling the dumplings, it’s essential to let them float
# 开锅就漂
Once the water is boiling, they should be floating
# 我们有一句话叫开锅煮馅 闭锅煮皮
We have a saying that uncover it to cook the filling and cover it to cook the skin
# 开锅了 开锅咱就不用盖了
It’s boiling right now, then we can take the lid off
# 有时候像茴香馅
Sometimes, for fillings like fennel
# 有时候为了保持茴香让它绿
In order to keep them green
# 打馅儿的时候那里边还可以捏点碱
We can have some alkali in the fillings
# 茴香就不是黄的了 就是绿的
Then the fennel won’t turn yellow and stay green
# 纯韭菜馅的也可以搁一点碱
Some alkali also works for pure chive fillings
# 这饺子快好了
It’s almost ready
# 再一压 倍儿骨立
Push it into the water a little bit. They are so plump
# 跟小猪似的饱满光亮 鼓起来
Like little pigs, all swollen and bright
# 你看这馅 韭菜特别绿
Look at the fillings, the chives are so green
# 韭菜馅这颜色不能太重了
The color of fillings with chives cannot be too dark
# 先给大爷来一个
Let’s give Daye one first
# 这个必须得您先来了
Your turn first this time
# 每回都是我们先吃
We always eat first
# 今天必须您吃第一口
Today you have to be the first
# 师父您先来
Master, please
# 好吃啊
So good
# 亮子吃饭就是猛 我是一口一个
Liangzi eats so fast. Yeah I eat one dumpling per bite
# 不是光一口 就直接下手 武吃
Not only that. You also use your hands
# 这里边海参吃着倍脆
The sea cucumbers inside are so crunchy
# 这个虾 说句实话
To be honest
# 这个饺子馅您看
For the fillings,
# 虾起了至关重要的作用 倍儿弹吃着
The shrimps play a very important role. It tastes so crunchy
# 其实会做饭的人
For people who know how to cook
# 我跟你说 你慢慢体验吧
Let me tell you, just experience it
# 会做饭的人第一他疼媳妇
People who cook care about their wives
# 顾家还有什么
Also take responsibilities for their families
# 他调理性的特别强
Can organize everything well
# 这个饺子你看似简单一个吃食
The dumplings seem to be very simple
# 他从和面 到饺子到我们嘴里
But he did a really good job from making doughs, making dumplings to cooking them
# 成型这个过程
The whole process
# 每个环节他拿捏的都非常到位 非常好
Nice job on every step. Excellent!